Supun Nakandala

Phone: (+1) 812-558-6888 3232 EBU3B CSE Email: snakanda@eng.ucsd.edu 9500 Gilman Drive Web: scnakandala.github.io La Jolla, CA 92093

Research Interests My research interest lies broadly in the intersection of Systems and Machine Learning, an emerging area which is increasingly referred to as Systems for ML. In this space I operate as a data management researcher. Taking inspirations from classical data management techniques, I build new abstractions, algorithms, and systems to improve efficiency, scalability, and usability of machine learning workloads.

Education

University of California, San Diego, CA

Sept 2017 - Present

PhD, Computer Science. GPA: 3.96/4.00 Thesis Advisor: Prof. Arun Kumar

Courses: Database System Implementation, Advanced Data Analytics Systems, Data Models in Big Data Era, Advanced Compiler Design, Machine Learning, Recommender Systems and Web Mining, Algorithm Design and Analysis

University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka

Aug 2010 - April 2015

Bachelor of the Science of Engineering, Computer Science & Engineering.

GPA: 4.11/4.20.

Department Topper and Gold Medalist

Publications

Incremental and Approximate Inference for Faster Occlusion-based Deep CNN Explanations

Supun Nakandala, Arun Kumar, and Yannis Papakonstantinou

ACM SIGMOD 2019 (Honorable Mention for Best Paper Award)

Cerebro: Efficient and Reproducible Model Selection on Deep Learning Systems

Supun Nakandala, Yuhao Zhang, and Arun Kumar

ACM SIGMOD 2019 DEEM Workshop

VLDB 2019 Demo | SysML 2019 Demo

Demonstration of Krypton: Optimized CNN Inference for Occlusion-based Deep CNN Explanations

Allen Ordookhanians, Xin Li, Supun Nakandala, and Arun Kumar

Materialization Trade-offs for Feature Transfer from Deep CNNs for Multimodal Data Analytics

Supun Nakandala, Arun Kumar

SysML 2018 Short paper

Gendered Conversation in a Social Game-Streaming Platform Supun Nakandala, Giovani Cimpaglia, Norma Su, and Yong-Yeol Ahn AAAI ICWSM 2017

Apache Airavata Security Manager: Authentication and Authorization Implementations for a Multi-Tenant eScience Framework

Supun Nakandala, Hasini Gunasinghe, Suresh Marru, and Marlon Pierce IEEE e-Science 2016

Anatomy of the SEAGrid Science Gateway Supun Nakandala, Sudhakar Pamidigantam, Suresh Marru, Marlon Pierce NSF XSEDE 2016

Pre-Prints

Vista: Declarative Feature Transfer from Deep CNNs at Scale

Supun Nakandala, Arun Kumar

https://adalabucsd.github.io/papers/TR_2019_Vista.pdf

Resource-Efficient and Reproducible Model Selection on Deep Learning Systems

Supun Nakandala, Yuhao Zhang, and Arun Kumar

https://adalabucsd.github.io/papers/TR_2019_Cerebro.pdf

Compiling Classical ML Pipelines into Tensor Computations for One-size-fits-all Prediction Serving

Supun Nakandala, Gyeong-In Yu, Matteo Interlandi, and Markus Weimer https://adalabucsd.github.io/papers/TR_2019_Hummingbird.pdf

Ongoing Projects Project Hummingbird

Started June 2019

In the past few years several optimized systems have been developed for accelerating deep learning prediction serving. However, in many domains, classical ML methods are still widely used. In this project we try to answer the following question: Can we represent classical ML pipelines using tensor computations to reuse deep net prediction serving systems for classical ML prediction serving? To realize this goal, project Hummingbird takes inspiration from query processing/optimization techniques in RDBMSs and compiles classical ML pipelines into tensor computations. Experiments on realworld use cases show that Hummingbird enables significant speedups (even up to 10X) and seamless hardware acceleration for classical ML prediction serving compared to other existing systems.

Project Cerebro

Started September 2018

Deep Neural Networks are revolutionizing many ML applications. But there is a major bottleneck to wider adoption: the pain of model selection. This empirical process involves exploring the deep net architecture and hyper-parameters, often requiring hundreds of trials. Alas, most ML systems focus on training one model at a time, reducing throughput and raising costs; some also sacrifice reproducibility. We are developing Cerebro, which is a system to raise deep net model selection throughput at scale and ensure reproducibility. Cerebro uses a novel parallel execution strategy we call model hopper parallelism which is inspired by the multi-query optimization technique. Experiments on Criteo and ImageNet datasets show Cerebro offers up to 10X speedups and improves resource efficiency significantly compared to existing systems like Parameter Server, Horovod, and task-parallel tools.

Research Impact

Ideas from project Cerebro integrated into MADlib/Greenplum by Pivotal 2019 Cerebro system is being used by behavioral science researchers at UC San Diego medical school

"Gendered Conversation in a Social Game-Streaming Platform" paper gains lot of media attention and creates awareness about the bleak issue of sexism in online game streaming platforms

Apache Airavata science gateways middleware and the SEAGrid science gateway are widely used by computational science researches to execute and manage computational jobs on university clusters and national supercomputing infrastructure

Work Experience

Research Intern

June 2019 - Sept 2019

Microsoft Cloud Information Services Lab

Mentor: Matteo Interlandi, Markus Weimer

Translating classical machine learning pipelines into tensor computations for unified and faster scoring of machine learning models.

Research Software Developer

Oct 2015 - Aug 2017

Science Gateways Research Center - Indiana University

Manager: Marlon Pierce

Developed Apache Airavata, which is a software framework to compose, manage, execute, and monitor large scale applications and workflows on distributed computing resources such as local clusters, supercomputers, computational grids, and computing clouds.

Teaching Experience Teaching Assistant - Advanced Data Analytics Systems

UCSD - Spring 2019

Scholarships and Awards

NSF travel award to attend ACM SIGMOD 2019

NSF - 2019

Gold Medal for the Best Academic Performance University of Moratuwa - 2015

Travel award to attend 4^{th} South Asia Workshop on Research

Frontiers in Computing

National University of Singapore - 2014

Mahapola Higher Education Merit Scholarship Govt. of Sri Lanka - 2010

Technical Talks

Incremental and Approximate Inference for Faster Occlusion-based Deep CNN Explanations

ACM SIGMOD 2019

Cerebro: A System for Efficient and Reproducible Model Selection on Deep Learning Systems ACM SIGMOD 2019